<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Footprints]]></title>
  <subtitle><![CDATA[a Trackfellas blog]]></subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-10T11:04:08.000Z</updated>
  <id>http://blog.trackfellas.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Trackfellas team]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[info@trackfellas.com]]></email>
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[A Trackfella goes Philippines!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/2014/12/14/a-trackfella-goes-philippines/"/>
    <id>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2014/12/14/a-trackfella-goes-philippines/</id>
    <published>2014-12-14T20:14:26.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-10T11:04:08.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a first entry in this category I want to present you my upcoming travel to the Philippines. I planned the trip taking our last blog about <a href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/2014/12/how-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/" target="_blank" rel="external">10 steps to plan your prefect trip</a> into account. Due to the high season during Christmas and New Years Eve in the Philippines I had to book nearly everything in advance.  As a result of the trip planning I want to show you the planned route and my itinerary.</p>
<p><strong>Travel Route</strong></p>
<p>To visualize my travel route I used Google Maps Engine. The tool allows to create and share maps online. Here is a screen shot of the travel route:<br><img src="/2014/12/14/a-trackfella-goes-philippines/Philippines-Trip-2014.jpg"></p>
<p>The usability is quite poor as there is no possibility to create a connected route.<br><a id="more"></a></p>
<p>Also the result is not very pleasing as it does not show directions or any dates. At least it is possible to save your route online and share it with others. Here you find my map for my Philippines trip:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.google.com/maps/d/edit?mid=zrYZfx3FSo48.k0hvSW6HcMlg" target="_blank" rel="external">Google Maps Engine</a></p>
<img src="/2014/12/14/a-trackfella-goes-philippines/Philippines-Trip-2014.jpg">
<p>Visualizing and planning travel routes is one of the key features we want to achieve with <a href="http://trackfellas.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Trackfellas</a>. We will give travellers the possibility to document their trips and share their routes and experiences with other individual travellers in the community.</p>
<p><strong>Itinerary</strong></p>
<p>I saved my itinerary into an excel file to maintain an overview. It is not really clearly arranged and of course it would make more sense to have it together with my travel route. Nevertheless no convincing travel planning platform exists so far. Until we can offer you an interface to save your itinerary and travel route in one place the current solution must suffice&#8230;</p>
<p>Here you see the preliminary itinerary witch highlights marked in bold:<br><img src="/2014/12/14/a-trackfella-goes-philippines/Itinerary-Philippines-Trip.png"></p>
<p> Planning this trip took me around 3 months, so now it is time to reap the tropical fruits of this work.</p>
<p>I will let you know, how it worked out!</p>
<p>See you soon from the other side of the planet,</p>
<p>Moritz from Trackfellas</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>As a first entry in this category I want to present you my upcoming travel to the Philippines. I planned the trip taking our last blog about <a href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/2014/12/how-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/">10 steps to plan your prefect trip</a> into account. Due to the high season during Christmas and New Years Eve in the Philippines I had to book nearly everything in advance.  As a result of the trip planning I want to show you the planned route and my itinerary.</p>
<p><strong>Travel Route</strong></p>
<p>To visualize my travel route I used Google Maps Engine. The tool allows to create and share maps online. Here is a screen shot of the travel route:<br><img src="/2014/12/14/a-trackfella-goes-philippines/Philippines-Trip-2014.jpg"></p>
<p>The usability is quite poor as there is no possibility to create a connected route.<br>]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Travels" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/categories/Travels/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[How to plan your perfect trip in 10 steps]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/"/>
    <id>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/</id>
    <published>2014-12-13T21:38:52.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-10T11:04:08.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src="/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/DSC01193.jpeg">
<p>Planning an individual trip abroad is a hassle and you need some experience and lots of information. With <a href="http://trackfellas.com" target="_blank" rel="external">trackfellas</a> we want offer travelers a platform for a community-driven exchange of travel experiences and routes to close that gap between printed guidebooks and travel recommendation websites. Starting from inspiration for your next travel over trip planning and booking to route documentation, rating and sharing you will find everything you need for your perfect trip in one place. Until we are ready, here are the best travel tips for planning your individual travels in the old-fashioned way:<br><a id="more"></a></p>
<ol>
<li><strong> Find awesome travel destinations</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>When the wanderlust hits, it’s time for a new adventure. There are endless possibilities to explore the world, you just have to get out and travel. And no worries with the right planning, travelling individually is not expensive, difficult or dangerous. Anywhere on this planet there is some place just for you!</p>
<img src="/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/DSC01587.jpeg">
<p>How to find it is the most inspiring and fun part of travelling besides the trip itself. Look out for beautiful destinations and activities and dream yourself away. Train rides in crowded India, a legendary road trip across the USA, island-hopping in the tropical Caribbean, trekking the mystic Inka trail, hitchhiking through cultural Europe, dog sledding in the white wilderness of Siberia, biking along the majestic great Wall of China, caravan tour in the hot Sahara, diving at the remarkable Great Barrier Reef or sailing around the world, everything is possible!</p>
<p>Let your desires and preferences as well as your budget and available time help you with your decision. Write down what you want to do and research for stunning places and special activities. For exclusive information ask friends, read through travel blogs and forums, hit the travel books or search in travel recommendation websites. Check as well for local festivals during your stay. These might turn your trip into something very special. You may also look for travel warnings from your government. But don&#8217;t take them too serious, for getting a comparison I recommend to read the travel warnings of your home country. Also mind the spoken languages in your chosen destination. In most frequent tourist spots either English, Spanish or French is spoken, often related to the former colonial rulers. Choose a few destinations and check your calendar when and for how long you are free to travel.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong> Travel duration and season</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>The best time to start planning your trip is 2 &#8211; 3 months before the planned departure. First count the days you are free to travel, also consider the jetlag once you return home, which may knock you out for another few days. The longer you can stay abroad, the better you will be able to get to know the country, its inhabitants and culture and also the airfare will reflect less on your daily budget. Set a date, but remain flexible for your departure within a week.</p>
<img src="/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/winter-city-2.jpg">
<p>The actual season you are going to travel affects your trip tremendously with prices differing by 30-40%. During public holidays, local as well as in the countries you are traveling to, the tourist spots are much more crowded, often reservations are necessary, although this doesn&#8217;t have to be the best season for holiday. Have also a look when and why there is an off-season, where often discounts are offered, but this might in many cases be related to bad weather conditions or other facts, which make traveling unpopular. You can check climate diagrams for certain places to find the best season for yourself. Also notice the further you are from the equator the bigger difference between the amount of daylight during winter and summer exists.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong> Total cost and flight booking</strong></li>
</ol>
<img src="/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/Sky-and-airplane.jpg">
<p>To get an overview of the necessary cash needed for your trip you should have a quick look at some guidebooks for a summary of costs or just check at booking website like <a href="http://hostelworld.com" target="_blank" rel="external">hostelworld.com</a> or <a href="http://booking.com" target="_blank" rel="external">booking.com</a> for the average cost of a backpackers hostel or hotel. Accomodation is mostly the biggest cost part besides airfares. These you can easily check online via flight search engines, like <a href="http://kayak.com" target="_blank" rel="external">kayak.com</a> or <a href="http://skyscanner.com" target="_blank" rel="external">skyscanner.com</a>. Also select airports nearby your planned destination and check all the potential flight connections with flexible dates. Intercontinental flights are normally cheaper mid-week and off-hours, if you book round trip and in average you get the best price three month before departure. Follow the price trend for several days or weeks for finding special offers. Have an eye as well on error fares websites like <a href="http://holidaypirates.com" target="_blank" rel="external">holidaypirates.com</a> which promotes incredible cheap tickets, especially when you are flexible in time and destination. By comparing the necessary costs with the amenities of the foreseen travel region you have a good base to choose your favorite destination.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong> Visa &amp; vaccinations</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Before planning your trip in detail check the two v’s. Are there any visa restrictions of your home country for your chosen destinations? Often you get a visa-on-arrival for around 1 month. For some countries you have to get a visa in advance, so make sure you will get it in time and your trip inside the country doesn’t exceed the maximum permitted stay. If so you can either leave the country during your trip and reenter to get a new visa or sometimes it is possible to extend your visa at immigration offices.</p>
<p>Vaccinations are very useful, although for some diseases like Malaria, HIV or Dengue fever no proper immunization exists. Inform yourself about local diseases and discuss potential risks with your doctor. Some vaccinations or drugs can be very costly, so better check before if you really need it and if your health insurance refunds them. Get the vaccinations in time, because some need multiple doses, which can require the first vaccination already weeks before your trip. Many countries even refuse entry, if you are coming from an affected country without having a mandatory vaccination, like yellow fever. So bring along your vaccination certificate.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong> Plan your travel route</strong></li>
</ol>
<img src="/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/map.jpg">
<p>Congratulations you found your personal best travel destination! Check once again the flight connection and finally book the best option. Get yourself a guidebook for the countries or regions you are going to visit. Although there are some online travel guides, you don’t want to miss them when you are stuck in the middle of nowhere with no battery or wifi around. If you want to visit more than one country some publishers offer transnational guidebooks of regions or countries. Lonely Planet is the most popular travel guide, but this also means to be inside the backpacker’s mainstream. Other recommended guidebooks for individual travelers are rough guides (english), Loose Travel Handbücher (german), Michael Müller Individualreisen (german) and Guide du routard (french). With this tool in hand you can start to plan your travel route. Anyhow if you prefer to go spontaneously on your trip you may skip the following part, but make sure you don’t get stuck during high season. Alternatively you ask online travel agencies specialized on individual trips like <a href="http://wandertrvl.com" target="_blank" rel="external">wandertrvl.com</a> for booking assistance for an extra fee. Guidebooks often suggest the best place to visit and offer prefixed travel routes. You could just copy them for your trip, but I recommend you create an individual travel route, except you want to travel the beaten track. At least your guidebook will help you find the best locations for your planned activities, hotels and transportation. Starting from your place of arrival, where you should spend one or two nights to get acclimatized and get rid of the jetlag you can check where to go next. Write down which places you want to visit and make sure you have enough free time for your everything planned. Find out about existing connections between two places in your travel guide or have a look at transportation search engines like <a href="http://rome2rio.com" target="_blank" rel="external">rome2rio.com</a> (worldwide), <a href="http://goeuro.com" target="_blank" rel="external">goeuro.com</a> (Europe) <a href="http://12go.asia" target="_blank" rel="external">12go.asia</a> (Southeast Asia) or <a href="http://roadtrippers.com" target="_blank" rel="external">roadtrippers.com</a> (road trips in USA). Some transportation is only available on certain days of the week so search with flexible dates. Collect all relevant information and save it together with your loose itinerary as an excel file in a cloud storage to have it always online with you.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong> Transportation and hotel booking</strong></li>
</ol>
<img src="/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/DSC07024.jpeg">
<p>Once you found your route either check first for important activities or for accommodation. This can become very complex, when transportation, accommodation and your intended activity all depend on each other. So don’t loose the overview, always have an alternative ready and adjust your itinerary if necessary. I really recommend booking ahead at least a hotel at your place of arrival. You stay fully flexible and you don’t have the hassle of searching for a place to sleep in an unknown city after an exhausting flight. Making a reservation or booking accommodation always makes sense in tourist hot spots or during high season. Special days like Christmas, New Years Eve or your own birthdays shouldn’t be left to chance. On the other hand, the more you book ahead, the less flexible you are to change your initial route while travelling. You can research for best accommodations at <a href="http://tripadvisor.com" target="_blank" rel="external">tripadvisor.com</a>, whereby contacting directly the hotel and making a reservation is often cheaper than booking at hotel portals and enables you to ask specific questions. A smart and cheap alternative is <a href="http://Airbnb.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Airbnb.com</a>, where you can rent anything from private rooms to entire houses. <a href="http://Couchsurfing.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Couchsurfing.com</a> offers a platform to find a place to sleep in a private home for free. When you are traveling on a budget this can be the perfect choice, but always check ratings to make sure you get a well-minded and mannered host. Booking transportation ahead is apart from flights often more complicated. Check out <a href="http://rome2rio.com" target="_blank" rel="external">rome2rio.com</a> or ask at your hotel nearby, if they can book the transportation for you in advance. In countries and regions with good backpacker infrastructure, such as Southeast Asia it is normally not necessary to book general transportation in advance.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong> Activities booking</strong></li>
</ol>

<p>You should now already have a plan what to do, where and when. Your guidebook will probably list some agencies for your planned activities. Most of the activities can be booked once you are on-site. For popular activities during high season or in special locations with limited numbers of daily tourists like diving in national parks, visiting crowded sights or going on a tour for several days making a reservation or booking ahead can be really useful. Contact the agency directly for making a reservation or book at <a href="http://getyourguide.com" target="_blank" rel="external">getyourguide.com</a></p>
<ol>
<li><strong> Bank &amp; credit card</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Get yourself a credit card without bank charges and fees for usage abroad. Many Internet banks offer such service those days. Also inform your bank about your upcoming travel, so that your transactions are not suspected to be illegal and your card doesn’t get blocked. Better have an additional card with you, in case one stops working or gets blocked nevertheless.</p>
<p><strong>9.  Travel insurance</strong></p>
<p>Now that you set up your perfect route nothing can go wrong?! Almost. You definitely want to have a health insurance with cover abroad to get the best medical treatment in case anything happens while travelling. And best medical treatment still means in many less developed countries less quality than in western countries. Ask your health insurance for further information. Depending on your travel expenses and your flexibility you might consider getting a travel insurance. It covers you and your expenses, when your camera breaks, your flights gets canceled, you have to return home earlier due to sickness or even have to cancel your trip before leaving.</p>
<p><strong>10. Enjoy your trip</strong></p>

<p>Finally the day comes and you can start into your self-made adventure. Make sure you have a list of your travel itinerary, including transportation and hotel address and a copy of important documents. In many places you won’t have internet so it makes sense to print the details. Don&#8217;t forget your passport and have a great trip!</p>
<p>All these things are quite useful, but we are working on our platform <a href="http://trackfellas.com" target="_blank" rel="external">trackfellas.com</a> to get you all you need for your next trip in one. So if this guides was of any help, come back after your trip, tell us about your experience and document your trip so you can share your travel route on our platform!</p>
<p>If you like to be up to date, sign up for the newsletter our get in touch on social media!</p>
<img src="/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/DSC04348.jpeg">
<p>When you want help us growing the community and give us some credits for the travel tips share this link or add our tag #trackfellas to your travel pictures or blog.</p>
<p>Thanks and see you!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Team trackfellas</p>
<h1 id="trackfellas">trackfellas</h1><p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Photo credits: Photos by Unsplash.com and Lukas Hofmann from his photography blog <a href="http://www.phoho.de" target="_blank" rel="external">www.phoho.de</a></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<img src="/2014/12/13/How-to-plan-your-perfect-trip-in-10-steps/DSC01193.jpeg">
<p>Planning an individual trip abroad is a hassle and you need some experience and lots of information. With <a href="http://trackfellas.com">trackfellas</a> we want offer travelers a platform for a community-driven exchange of travel experiences and routes to close that gap between printed guidebooks and travel recommendation websites. Starting from inspiration for your next travel over trip planning and booking to route documentation, rating and sharing you will find everything you need for your perfect trip in one place. Until we are ready, here are the best travel tips for planning your individual travels in the old-fashioned way:<br>]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="booking" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/booking/"/>
    
      <category term="planning" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/planning/"/>
    
      <category term="route" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/route/"/>
    
      <category term="tips" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/tips/"/>
    
      <category term="trackfellas" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/trackfellas/"/>
    
      <category term="travel" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/travel/"/>
    
      <category term="trip" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/trip/"/>
    
      <category term="travel planning" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/categories/travel-planning/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Introducing Trackfellas]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/2014/12/12/Introducing-Trackfellas/"/>
    <id>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2014/12/12/Introducing-Trackfellas/</id>
    <published>2014-12-12T21:58:34.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-10T11:04:08.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello World,</p>
<p>We proudly present you Trackfellas,  a revolutionary community-based platform for travel routes.</p>
<img src="/2014/12/12/Introducing-Trackfellas/logo.png">
<p>Individual travel is our shared passion. However planning individual trips is a huge hassle. You find nowadays lots of information about certain places, but the biggest problem is to link a chosen destination to a travel route. For that travelers still have to rely on printed guidebooks to plan their best route. Most individual travelers face this problem, either before or during their travels. So far there no solution exists, which allows travelers to upload their own travel route, rate their experiences or find routes of others. Their knowledge remains mainly restricted to their friends or gets buried in one of countless travel blogs.</p>
<p>After planning trips all over the world, Moritz had the idea of building a community-based platform for travel routes. Together with Niklas and Lucas we dug deeper into solving the problem and devised a unified solution for traveler needs.</p>
<img src="/2014/12/12/Introducing-Trackfellas/IMG_5402.jpg">
<p>Starting from discovering routes of other travelers, to planning your own travel route on a map, booking certain parts of your journey, documenting your trip, rating your experiences and sharing it on social media and within the community, Trackfellas offers everything you need in one place. Now comes the best thing, we will offer all that as a free service with perfect usability.</p>
<p>Eventually we will develop a marketplace for individual trips, where routes and itineraries created by travelers are matched with personalized travel packages crafted by travel agencies.</p>
<p>Until we can provide you a beta version of <a href="http://trackfellas.com" target="_blank" rel="external">trackfellas.com</a>, we will keep you-up-to-date about Trackfellas, our development and news in our blog. We will also feed you with travel stories, exclusive travel tips and much more that makes you want to grab your backpack.</p>
<p>If you want to help us growing, give us some feedback at the comments, sign up for our newsletter and spraid the word.</p>
<p>See you,</p>
<p>Team trackfellas</p>
<h1 id="trackfellas">trackfellas</h1>]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>Hello World,</p>
<p>We proudly present you Trackfellas,  a revolutionary community-based platform for travel routes.</p>
<img src="/2014/]]>
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Trackfellas" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/categories/Trackfellas/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>