<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Footprints]]></title>
  <subtitle><![CDATA[a Trackfellas blog]]></subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-25T06:01:49.000Z</updated>
  <id>http://blog.trackfellas.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Trackfellas team]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[info@trackfellas.com]]></email>
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Travel Route Philippines: Visayas & Manila]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/"/>
    <id>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/</id>
    <featured>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/whaleshark.jpg</featured>
    <published>2015-03-23T13:18:37.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-25T06:01:49.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>III. Part: Trip Route (Visayas &amp; Manila)</h2>
<p>This is the subsequent blog of the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/" title="Philippines Island Hopping Trip">Philippines Island Hopping Trip</a>, with the previous part <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/" title="Travel Route for Palawan">Travel Route for Palawan</a> including the travel route.</p>
<p>Be excited for whale sharks, typhoons and Jeepney rides!</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/whaleshark.jpg">  
The Philippines is one of the few places, where you can snorkel and dive with these gentle giants of the sea.
<a id="more"></a>
<h4>8. Puerto Princessa, Palawan - Iloilo, Panay - Caticlan, Panay - Boracay, Panay</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Transportation<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           29.12.14<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong>       651 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>       11 hours</p>
<blockquote>
<p><font color="black"> <strong>1.Transportation:</strong> 29.12.14 / 10:25 - 11:30 Puerto Princessa - Iloilo<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> National flight (5J 262)<br>
<strong>Airline:</strong> <em><a href="https://www.cebupacificair.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Cebu Pacific</a></em> (2/5)<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 430 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 1 hours<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 83 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> This flight connection exists only on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Taxis at the Iloilo Airport offer somehow ridiculous prices, try to get a cab outside of the airport.</font></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>2. Transportation:</strong>     Van from Iloilo to Caticlan (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Van<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 220 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 5 hour<br>
<strong>Costs:</strong> 10 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> We shared a private van with other travelers, so we had enough space and stopped for lunch on the way. Alternatively you can take a bus from the Takbak Terminal for 7 €.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>3. Transportation:</strong> Caticlan - Boracay (2/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Ferry<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 1 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 20 min<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 5 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> You have to buy seriously three different tickets: terminal fee, environmental fee and the ferry ticket, which is by the way the cheapest one. The ferry runs 24/7. On Boracay take a tricycle to your final destination.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4>9. Boracay, Panay (2/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Small island<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           29.12.14 - 2.1.15<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Boracay was once an exotic small island with fisherman villages and a 4 km long white beach. The beach remained, but nowadays it turned into a mass tourism place like Kuta on Bali or Ballermann on Mallorca, with hotel bunkers, McDonalds and Starbucks right at the beach and shopping malls, of course! Expect mostly package holiday tourists, interesting enough they are from all over the world, like China, Korea, Japan, Russia, Europe, USA, Australia or South Africa. That’s why you will also find all kinds of international restaurants, but also with European prices! There are many bars and clubs with mostly techno music, but don’t expect beach parties and if there are, like on New years Eve, the area is fenced and you have to pay 10 € entrance. We also didn’t have luck with the weather, but nevertheless I would not recommend people to go there. This is not the real Philippines…<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> You can dive and windsurf on Boracay as well!<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> You are not alone on Boracay island!</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/boracay.jpg">  
<p><strong>Accommodation:</strong>  <em><a href="http://www.orchidsboracay.com/index.htm" target="_blank" rel="external">Orchids Resort</a></em> (2/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> B&amp;B<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 52€ per night AC-room with double bed and private bath<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Bamboo Hotel with orchid garden, 100m away from the beach (station 3). Thin walls and cockroach alarm!<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Try to get a fan to save money or try next door at Bora Bora Inn or Dave’s Straw Hat Inn.  Book in advance during peak season, like Xmas, New Years Eve or Easter.</p>
<p><strong>Food:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Bei Kurt &amp; Magz</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Cheap beer during happy hour (60 Cents) and German food.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Swiss Inn</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Good drinks and good cheese fondue for 30 € for 2 persons.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>D’Talipapa Market</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Market<br>
You can buy fresh fish or seafood at the seafood market and nearby restaurants, so called palutuan or paluto will cook it as you wish for you for a small fee, around 3 €. Even when you bargain good (half of the first price) it will not be cheaper than in other restaurants, but it’s fun somehow to hunt your own food.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Entertainment:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Pat’s Creek Bar</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Beach Bar<br>
Live music at the beach and cold beer buckets.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Exit Bar</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Beach Bar &amp; Disco<br>
Dancing in the sand to good electronic music, which is really rare on this side of the planet.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Picture:</strong> Party hard at the beach during a typhoon on new years eve.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/newyearseve.jpg">  
<p><strong>Activities:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em><a href="http://whitebeachdivers.com" target="_blank" rel="external">White Beach Divers</a></em> (missed)<br>
Type: Dive<br>
Cost: 58 € for 2 dives<br>
Comment: Due to the bad weather we couldn’t go diving. There is supposed to be an airplane and container ship wreck nearby in 30 m depth.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Cliff Diving</em> (missed)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Tour<br>
<strong>Tour Operator:</strong> <em><a href="http://www.arielspoint.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Ariel’s Point</a></em><br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 6 hours<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Boat<br>
<strong>Food:</strong> BBQ and unlimited drinks, including beer and mixed drinks<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 38 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> We didn’t have enough time and although it is not cheap, it looks like big fun; The deal is you get drunk and jump from 15 m high cliffs.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>10. Boracay - Caticlan, Panay - Kalibo, Panay - Cebu City, Cebu</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Transportation<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           2.1.15<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong>       301 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>       8 hours<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> We flew from Kalibo, because the flights were much cheaper than from the Airport in Caticlan and you get from Caticlan only to Manila.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> In case you are on Panay during middle of January, you should check out the Ati-Atihan festival in Kalibo. It is the biggest carnival-like festival of the Philippines on the 3. weekend of January. Definitely book accommodation ahead!</p>
<blockquote>
<p><font color="red"><strong>1. Transportation:</strong>  Boracay - Caticlan (1/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Ferry<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 1 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 1,5 hours!<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 3 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> It seemed like half of Boracays visitors left on the 2.1. so the ferry were totally overcrowded. It took us 1,5 hours instead of 15 min to get to Caticlan and we nearly missed our flight… again!<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Make sure you have enough extra time when headed to the airport.<br>
<font color="black"><br>
<strong>2. Transportation:</strong>    Van from Caticlan to Kalibo (2/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Van<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 70 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 1,5 hours<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 3 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> We bought the transfer ticket to Kalibo airport already at the ferry station in Boracay. The van was totally packed, we even had to put our baggage on our knees. This combined with not knowing whether we would make it in time to the airport made this drive unpleasant.</font></font></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>3. Transportation:</strong> 2.1.15 / 11:55 - 12:40 Kalibo - Cebu (1/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> National flight (5J 417)<br>
<strong>Airline:</strong> <em><a href="https://www.cebupacificair.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Cebu Pacific</a></em> (2/5)<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 230 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 1 hours<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 42 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Of course the airport was totally full of tourists as well. There was a long queue to get inside the airport, due to the bottleneck called x-ray machine. Luckily the plane had 2 hours delay, so we caught our flight, despite our late arrival.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> To get from the Airport to Cebu Uptown go to the international arrival terminal and take a white taxi (5 €) who are half the price than the yellow cabs from the national arrival!<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Just a normal situation at the overcrowded airports in the Philippines.</p>
</blockquote>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/cebu-pacific.jpg"> 
<h3>11. Cebu City, Cebu (3/5)</h3>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Big City<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           2.1. - 3.1.15<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Third biggest city of the Philippines with a colonial city center, good restaurants and hectic city life.</p>
<p><strong>Accommodation:</strong>  <em><a href="http://www.casaescano.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Casa Escano</a></em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> B&amp;B<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 41€ per night AC-room with double bed and private bath<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Old colonial hacienda in uptown with quite rooms and fantastic breakfast and great restaurant. This luxury has of course its price.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> For cheaper accommodation check out Cebu Guesthouse (12€ for fan room)</p>
<p><strong>Food:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Don Merto’s Deli &amp; Restaurant</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Restaurant of Casa Escano; Spanish-Filipino fusion and western food like burgers and sandwiches.</li>
</ul>
<p><font color="green"></font></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Mesa</em>, Ayala Terraces  (5/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Modern and best Filipino food we had so far. Try the Boneless Crispy Pata, a roasted pork knuckle for 10 € and enough for 2.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> In this complex next to the Ayala Mall you find lots of in- and outdoor bars and all kind of international restaurants.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> The Filiponos love roasted park, so do we :)</li>
</ul>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/mesa.jpg"> 
<p><font color="black"></font></p>
<p><strong>Entertainment:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>The Highlights</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Bar<br>
Cheap beer and drinks at the chic rooftop Bar of hotel Harold’s.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Mango Square Mall</em> (2/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Bar &amp; Disco Complex<br>
Many bars and clubs, who fight for every costumer. None of them looked really pleasant for us, also due to the prostitutes and their potential clients around.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sightseeing:</strong>        <em>Downtown</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> City walk<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 2 hours<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> From the old colonial city center not much remains, but you can visit by foot the quite nice Fort San Pedro, the basilica Minore de Santo Nino with the oldest holy relic of the country (Santo Nino) and the Magellan’s Cross and the colorful Carbon market with agricultural and handcraft products of Cebu.</p>
<h4>12. Cebu City, Cebu - Tan-Awan, Cebu</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Transportation<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           2.1.15</p>
<p><font color="red"><strong>Transportation:</strong>   Bus from Cebu via Oslob to Tan-Awan (1/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Bus<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 130 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 4,5 hours<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 5 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> The buses to the south of Cebu are leaving at the Southern Bus Terminal. The bus drive is actually quite nice, as long as you are not driving with the small buses with open windows. They are very packed, the bus stops every few minutes, because people hop on and off and you certainly seem to have hara-kiri drivers behind the steering wheel. With fear of death we had to change the bus and waited for a bigger one, as they can not accelerate as fast as the small buses can.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Take a big AC-bus, you will feel much more comfortable<br>
<font color="black"><br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Anyone needs a ride? Tricycles are the #1 vehicles for local transport. Funnily they look different on every island.</font></font></p>
 <img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/tricycles.jpg"> 
<h4>13. Tan-Awan, Oslob, Cebu (2/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Village<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           3.1. - 4.1. 15<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> This is the closest place for the whale shark watching. You can also stay in Oslob 9 km north or Dumaguete on Negros and get an early ride or boat to here. In Tan-Awan there is just a small stony beach and nothing to do at night.</p>
<p><strong>Accommodation:</strong>  <em><a href="https://bcdsplace.wordpress.com" target="_blank" rel="external">BCD’s Place</a></em> (2/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> B&amp;B<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 27 € per night AC-room with double bed and private bath<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Very unspectacular rooms, with plastic wrapped mattresses, but all in all very clean.</p>
<p><strong>Food:</strong> <em>Sunrise Grillhouse</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Friendly guitar playing staff is serving fresh fruits and simple food at the beachfront next door.</p>
<p><strong>Activities:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><em><a href="http://www.oslobwhalesharks.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Oslob Whale Shark Watching</a></em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Snorkeling or Diving<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 9 € from the boat (30 min), 18 € for snorkeling (30 min), 27 € + dive costs for diving (1 hour)<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> These biggest fish are absolutely fascinating, but unfortunately the local people made a tourist-money-making-machine out of them. They are always around between 7 and noon, because they get feed You get to this place, which is close to the beach by rowing boat. We snorkeled half an hour with around six whale sharks, who come really close to you, so that you have to pay attention not to get hit by their tail fin. Meeting these gentle giants in the wild and not having 30 other tourists around you is probably a much more sublime moment then here.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Be there early between 7 and 8 a.m. because during the day the whale sharks disappear, when they are full or there is too much trouble for them. You have a good chance to find whale sharks without feeding in Donsol at East Luzon.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Vis-a-vis with a whale shark is a bit scary, but luckily only dangerous for plankton!</li>
</ul>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/whaleshark-vis-a-vis.jpg">     
Tourists lined up as a string of pearls for swimming with the whale sharks is the other side of the medal...  
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/tourists-whaleshark.jpg">  
<ul>
<li><em>Boat trip to Sumilon Island</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Snorkeling, Beach<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 5 hours<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Boat (Outtrigger boat)<br>
<strong>Number of passengers:</strong> 2<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 27 € for  2 person for getting there and back<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> You can book a boat ride to Sumilon island. Ask if they can drop you at the reef for snorkeling.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> There is nothing on the island, beside a nice sandy beach, reefs and an exclusive beach resort. Food and drinks are supposed to be very expensive there (20 €), so better bring your own.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Sumilon Island as many other reefs between Cebu and Negros are great places for snorkeling and diving in the Philippines.</li>
</ul>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/reef.jpg">  
<h4>14. Tan-Awan, Cebu - Liloan, Cebu - Sibulan, Negros - Dumaguete, Negros</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Transportation<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           4.1.15<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong>       25 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>       2 hours</p>
<blockquote>
<p><font color="black"><strong>1. Transportation:</strong> Tan-Awan - Liloan (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Bus<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 10 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>  30 min<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 1,50 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Just stop any bus passing by and head down the road to the ferry terminal in Liloan.</font></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>2. Transportation:</strong> Liloan - Sibulan (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Ferry<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 7 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>  30 min<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 1 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> There are ferries leaving every 30 minutes from 5:00 until 7:30 p.m.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>3. Transportation:</strong>    Sibulan - Dumaguete (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Tricycle<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 6 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>  20 min<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 2 €</p>
</blockquote>
<h4>15. Dumaguete, Negros (4/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           City<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           4.1. - 5.1.15<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Dumaguete is said to be the city of friendly people, which we can confirm. When asking the price for tricycle ride, the answer was mostly “up to you”. We probably still paid too much, but this way it feels much more comfortable, then the usual bargaining. Although we had bad weather during our stay, which is obviously normal during that time of the year, we enjoyed our stay in Dumaguete. There is a nice waterfront with lots of small food stalls at night, manifold restaurants and some bars and clubs. It is also a good hub to explore the nearby underwater world.</p>
<p><strong>Accommodation:</strong>  <em><a href="http://haroldsmansion.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Harold’s Mansion</a></em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Hostel<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 15 € per night AC-room with double bed and private bath<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Cheap Backpacker’s hostel with free coffee, tea, water and Wi-Fi and a big rooftop with a restaurant. In house is the Harolds Dive Center, which offers trips to the whale shark watching in Oslob, Cebu, dive trips to Apo Island and dive safaris.</p>
<p><strong>Food:</strong>   <em>Bo’s Coffee</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Cafe<br>
Located at the seafront. Starbucks Filipino style with good coffee, unfortunately in paper cups.</p>
<p><strong>Activity:</strong>   <em>Diving at Apo Island</em> (missed)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Dive, Snorkeling<br>
<strong>Tour Operator:</strong> <em><a href="http://haroldsdivecenter.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Harolds Dive Center</a></em><br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> half day<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Boat (Outtrigger boat)<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 60 € for 3 dives<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> We didn’t have time left, but Apo Island is supposed to be one of the top 10 dive sites in the Philippines, including sharks, turtles, rays, barracudas and a beautiful macro life.</p>
<h4>16. Dumaguete, Negros - Manila, Luzon (2/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Transportation<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           5.1.15<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong>       660 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>       7 hours</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>1. Transportation:</strong> 5.1.15 / 13:55 - 15:10 Dumaguete - Manila (2/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> National flight (5J 628)<br>
<strong>Airline:</strong> <em><a href="https://www.cebupacificair.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Cebu Pacific</a></em> (2/5)<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 645 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 1 hour 15 min<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 77 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Guess what, the flight was delayed…</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>2. Transportation:</strong>  Manila Airport - Manila Ermita (2/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Taxi<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 15 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 2 hours<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 10 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Due to our late arrival we got caught in the rush hour. You can choose to go instead with the yellow cabs (cheapest, but in our case very long queue), white taxis (prepaid and more expensive, but “only” 30 min queue) or you get ripped of by one of the taxi touts, who will sell you a prepaid taxi for 25 €!<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> You might have more luck and less queueing one floor up at the departure hall. When the drivers don’t want to use their meter, make sure you don’t pay more then 14 € to Quezon City, 10 € to Ermita or 8 € to Malate or Makati.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4>17. Ermita, Manila, Luzon (4/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Megacity, Capital<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           5.1. - 7.1.15<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Manila does not have a good reputation, but more than any other metropolis in Southeast Asia it is an exciting melting pot of colonial heritage, business city, shopping malls, slum, Chinatown, American fast food restaurants, seafront, 24/7 nightlife and traffic jam.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> As most travelers will pass by Manila anyway it is worth staying here two to three days and explore the city. We decided to visit Manila at the end of our trip. To get around fast avoid the rush hour from 7 - 9 a.m. and 5 - 8 p.m.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> The normal madness on Manilas streets.</p>
   
<p><strong>Accommodation:</strong>  _<a href="http://www.oasispark.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Oasis Paco Park Hotel</a>_, Ermita (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Hotel<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 36 € per night for huge superior room with AC, TV, double bed and private bath, free newspaper, free Wi-Fi and welcome drink.<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Luxurious Hotel with pool in a quiet area; Good price-quality ratio;<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> For cheaper accommodation check out Wanderers Guesthouse in<br>
Malate (16€ per night for a double room)</p>
<p><font color="green"> <strong>Transportation:</strong>    <em>Driving with a Jeepney</em>  (5/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Minibus<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> Starting with 10 Cent<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Just jump in any Jeepney and take a ride, but better not during rush hour, else you might get a carbon monoxide poisoning.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Jeepneys drive on fixed routes, who are written in front of the windshield or on the side of the Jeepney. If you are not sure you can ask the driver or other passengers to let you  know once you reached your destination.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Cheap hop-on hop-off tour with a Jeepney. You will just have no clue where you are when getting off.</font></p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/Jeepney.jpg">    
<p><font color="black"><strong>Food:</strong>   <em>Zamboanga</em>, Ermita (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Try the seafood platter for 10€, which serves two. There are also live folk dances from 8 - 9 p.m.</font></p>
<p><strong>Entertainment:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><em>White Moon Bar</em>, Intramuros (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Bar<br>
Sunset Bar at the 2. floor of the Ocean Park<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> The sun goes down over the Bay of Manila, while a father and his son are trying to get a catch in their small canoe. Rich and poor is in Manila just a heartbeat away.</li>
</ul>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/manila-bay.jpg">
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Library Comedy Bar</em>, Malate (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Comedy Bar<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 3 €<br>
Filipino Comedy, unfortunately mostly in Tagalog</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Hanging out around the Remedios Circle</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Bar Complex<br>
Crazy nightlife 24/7; Cheap food and drinks at food stalls in M. Adriatico.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Club ZZYZX</em>, Malate (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Disco<br>
We had lots of fun in this packed “club” at the Remedios circle, not because of the strange techno music, more for the ridiculous party rules, like not to dance with drinks in your hand, “bouncer” securities  everywhere and the crazy local party mood! It is worth it checking it out, it is free, at least on Mondays and there were mostly locals around.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sightseeing:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Colonial heritage in Intramuros</em>, Manila (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> City walk<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> half day<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Former Spanish colonial quarter, which got destroyed during the second world war. Reconstruction ongoing, but you can feel nevertheless the moving history here.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Transportation:</strong>       <em>Horse-drawn carriage in Intramuros</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Carriage ride<br>
<strong>Costs:</strong> 7 € for 30 min<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Some stories from the coachmen and relaxation for the feet.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>San Agustin Church</em>, Intramuros, Manila (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Church &amp; Museum<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 1 €<br>
Nice and only original church left in Intramuros</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Fort Santiago</em>, Intramuros, Manila (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Fort<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 1,50 €<br>
Former Spanish military defense base and heart of the old Manila; Includes as well a museum of the imprisoned and killed national hero Rizal<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> At the reconstructed gate of Fort Santiago in Intramuros.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/intramuros.jpg"> 
<hr>
<p><strong>Epilog:</strong> I hope we could give you some travel inspirations and an idea of how a travel route through the Philippines could look like. For a more authentic feeling you have to get yourself on one of the 7107 islands of the Philippines. We would be glad to hear from your experiences at the comments or by adding our hashtag #trackfellas to your posts.</p>
<p>Keep in touch for more travel stories and routes worldwide and sign up for our <a href="http://trackfellas.com/#signup" target="_blank" rel="external">Beta program</a> to experience the ultimate way of traveling as a Trackfella.</p>
<p>It was a pleasure,</p>
<p><strong>Moritz from Trackfellas</strong></p>
<hr>
<h6><em>Note: The publisher does not accept responsibility for the correctness, accuracy or completeness of the information.</em></h6>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<h2>III. Part: Trip Route (Visayas &amp; Manila)</h2>
<p>This is the subsequent blog of the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/" title="Philippines Island Hopping Trip">Philippines Island Hopping Trip</a>, with the previous part <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/" title="Travel Route for Palawan">Travel Route for Palawan</a> including the travel route.</p>
<p>Be excited for whale sharks, typhoons and Jeepney rides!</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/whaleshark.jpg">  
The Philippines is one of the few places, where you can snorkel and dive with these gentle giants of the sea.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Cebu" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Cebu/"/>
    
      <category term="Manila" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Manila/"/>
    
      <category term="Philippines" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Philippines/"/>
    
      <category term="Visayas" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Visayas/"/>
    
      <category term="island hopping" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/island-hopping/"/>
    
      <category term="travel guide" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/travel-guide/"/>
    
      <category term="trip inspiration" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/trip-inspiration/"/>
    
      <category term="whale shark" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/whale-shark/"/>
    
      <category term="travel route" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/categories/travel-route/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Travel Route Philippines]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/"/>
    <id>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/</id>
    <featured>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/hero-image.jpg</featured>
    <published>2015-03-18T14:51:50.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-21T16:53:37.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Philippines Island Hopping Trip</h2>
<p>Trackfellas presents you the best travel routes worldwide. Until we can offer you a beta version of <a href="http://trackfellas.com" target="_blank" rel="external">trackfellas.com</a>, we will feed you with travel routes on our freshly redesigned blog, with all the valuable information for your next trip.</p>
<p><strong>We proudly present our first travel route, which brings us to the marvelous islands of the Philippines!</strong></p>
<p>This blogpost is separated into 3 parts, general  <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/" title="Trip Information">Trip Information</a>, the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/" title="Travel Route for Palawan">Travel Route for Palawan</a> and the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/" title="Travel Route for the Visayas and Manila">Travel Route for the Visayas and Manila</a>. Enjoy reading and keep in touch for more travel routes on our blog or follow us on facebook, twitter or google+.</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/hero-image.jpg">  
Sun, Beach and Island Beauties somewhere in the island world of Palawan, Philippines. 
<a id="more"></a>
<h2>I. Part: Travel Information</h2>
<p>Here you find the overview of the travel route and the most important facts including ratings in brackets from 1 (horrible) to 5 (awesome) for the described three weeks trip and the Philippines itself.</p>
<h3>Trip Summary: Philippines Island Hopping Trip (4/5)</h3>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=zrYZfx3FSo48.k0hvSW6HcMlg"></iframe>
<p><strong>Description:</strong>        Along the coast to the best beaches and islands of the Philippines<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Backpacking Holidays<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>               15.12.2014 - 7.1.2015<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>           23 days<br>
<strong>Weather:</strong> 3/5 (20 - 30 °C, sunny and hot in Palawan, cloudy and rainy with a small typhoon in the Visayas)<br>
<strong>Activities:</strong>             Beach, Snorkeling, Diving, Nightlife, Sailing, Sightseeing, Nature<br>
<strong>Safety:</strong>             4/5 (Pay attention in big cities like Manila)<br>
<strong>Number of travelers:</strong>     2 (Couple)<br>
<strong>Required travel skills:</strong>     Easy<br>
<strong>Trip suited for travelers:</strong>  with kids; as single woman; as group travel; as young traveler;<br>
<strong>Total Costs on-site:</strong>        1500 - 2000 €<br>
<strong>+ Round flight fare:</strong>       500 - 1000 €</p>
<div class="left"> 
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/cost-distribution.jpg"> 
</div>
<p><strong>Accommodation category:</strong>     Middle-class (AC, TV, private bath)<br>
<strong>Total distance:</strong>         2800 km<br>
<strong>Main transportation:</strong>        Flight (1600km), Van (580 km),  Boat (300 km), Bus (150 km)<br>
<strong>+ Round flight distance:</strong>   22000 km</p>
<h3>Trip Destination:</h3>
<p><strong>Country:</strong>            Philippines, Southeast Asia<br>
<strong>Languages:</strong>          English, Tagalog<br>
<strong>Climate:</strong>            Tropical, hot and humid climate, influenced by the monsoon<br>
<strong>Seasons:</strong>            Rainy season from June - November with strong rainfall and many typhoons coming from the pacific. Dry season from December - March with less rainfall and an average temperature around 25°C. Generally there is more rainfall on the pacific coast. Hot and dry season from April - June with much sun and temperatures up to 40°C.<br>
<strong>Travel period:</strong>          Best travel time is December - March with the least rainfall and comfortable temperatures between February and March; High season is from December - February, especially between Christmas and New years Eve, during Chinese New Year and Easter, when many hotels in touristic places like Boracay add surcharges of up to 50%.<br>
<strong>Visa:</strong>               Visa-on-arrival for 30 days for EU travelers, extendable to 59 days at the bureau of immigration or at Manila Airport for 55€. Valid passport for 6 month necessary.<br>
<strong>Currency conversion:</strong>    47 PHP = 1 €<br>
<strong>Health Care:</strong>            No mandatory vaccination, but vaccination against tetanus, diphtheria, polio, and hepatitis A is important, additionally Hepatitis B and typhus and malarone as standby-therapy makes sense; In Palawan there are no hospitals, besides in Puerto Princessa. Bring along your own first-aid kit<br>
<strong>Travel warnings:</strong>        Don’t travel to the unsafe Muslim-dominated southwestern islands and be aware of strong monsoon during the rain season. For further detailed information check travel warnings of your government, for example of the <a href="http://travel.state.gov/content/passports/english/alertswarnings/philippines-travel-warning.html" target="_blank" rel="external">U.S. Bureau of Consular Affairs</a> and the <a href="http://www.pagasa.dost.gov.ph" target="_blank" rel="external">Philippine Weather Service</a> for weather warnings for the Philippines.</p>
<h3>Trackfella:</h3>
<div class="left"> 
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/trackfella-moritz.jpg">
</div>
<p><strong>Name:</strong>               Moritz<br>
<strong>Gender &amp; Age:</strong>       Male, 29<br>
<strong>From:</strong>               Berlin, Germany<br>
<strong>Member since:</strong>       2014<br>
<strong>Skills:</strong> Globetrotter<br>
<strong>Submitted Routes:</strong>       1<br>
<strong>Contact:</strong>            <a href="mailto:moritz@trackfellas.com" target="_blank" rel="external">moritz@trackfellas.com</a></p>
<h3>Round Trip:</h3>
<p><strong>Transportation:</strong>         International flight<br>
<strong>Connection:</strong> Frankfurt - Beijing - Manila<br>
<strong>Airline:</strong>            <em><a href="http://www.airchina.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Air China</a></em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Cost for round trip:</strong>        655 € + 10 € Terminal Fee<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong>           11000 km</p>
<h4>Inbound Transportation: Frankfurt - Manila (3/5)</h4>
<p>15.12.14 / 14:05 - 06:15 +1     Frankfurt International - Beijing (CA 966)<br>
16.12.14 / 18:30 - 23:20    Beijing - Manila Ninoey Aquino (CA 629)<br>
07.01.15 / 06:40 - 11:20    Manila Ninoy Aquino - Beijing (CA 180)<br>
07.01.15 / 13:55 - 17:15    Beijing - Frankfurt International (CA 931)<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>           26 hours<br>
<strong>Stopover:</strong>           12 hours (Beijing, China)<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Cheap flight, but not the best connection and departure time as you fly during the day and arrive in the middle of the night to  Beijing. Possibility to get a 72-hour Visa-free transit in Beijing; Visited the city center and the forbidden city. You can get cheap there by train and metro. Alternatively you can visit the Great Wall of China within a half day tour from the airport as well. When travelling in winter make sure you have warm clothes as Beijing can become very cold.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Taxi trips from the airport can be really expensive, so better count and negotiate twice.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Blue sky! and freezing cold (-7°C) at the Tiananmen Square and Forbidden City in Beijing.</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/beijing.jpg">
<h4>Outbound flight:       Manila - Frankfurt (3/5)</h4>
<p>07.01.15 / 06:40 - 11:20    Manila Ninoy Aquino - Beijing (CA 180)<br>
07.01.15 / 13:55 - 17:15    Beijing - Frankfurt International (CA 931)<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>           17,5 hours<br>
<strong>Stopover:</strong>           2,5 hours (Beijing, China)<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Also not the best departure time as we had to leave our hotel already at 4 a.m. and the flight time made the jetlag even worse.</p>
<p>In the next part we will present you the travel route for the Philippines island hopping trip.<br>
Click here for the detailed trip description through <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/" title="Palawan">Palawan</a>, the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/" title="Visayas and Manila">Visayas and Manila</a></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<h2>Philippines Island Hopping Trip</h2>
<p>Trackfellas presents you the best travel routes worldwide. Until we can offer you a beta version of <a href="http://trackfellas.com">trackfellas.com</a>, we will feed you with travel routes on our freshly redesigned blog, with all the valuable information for your next trip.</p>
<p><strong>We proudly present our first travel route, which brings us to the marvelous islands of the Philippines!</strong></p>
<p>This blogpost is separated into 3 parts, general  <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/" title="Trip Information">Trip Information</a>, the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/" title="Travel Route for Palawan">Travel Route for Palawan</a> and the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/" title="Travel Route for the Visayas and Manila">Travel Route for the Visayas and Manila</a>. Enjoy reading and keep in touch for more travel routes on our blog or follow us on facebook, twitter or google+.</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/hero-image.jpg">  
Sun, Beach and Island Beauties somewhere in the island world of Palawan, Philippines.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Palawan" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Palawan/"/>
    
      <category term="Philippines" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Philippines/"/>
    
      <category term="Visayas" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Visayas/"/>
    
      <category term="island hopping" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/island-hopping/"/>
    
      <category term="travel guide" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/travel-guide/"/>
    
      <category term="trip inspiration" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/trip-inspiration/"/>
    
      <category term="travel route" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/categories/travel-route/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Travel Route Philippines: Palawan]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/"/>
    <id>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/</id>
    <featured>http://blog.trackfellas.com/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/view-from-matiloc-shrine.jpg</featured>
    <published>2015-03-16T13:53:50.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-25T06:01:49.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>II. Part: Trip Route (Palawan)</h2>
<p>Here you find the detailed description of the island hopping travel route through the Philippines, starting in Manila to Puerto Princessa. You can of course do the trip the other way around as well, TAO Philippines operates a few times per week in both directions.</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/view-from-matiloc-shrine.jpg">
View from the Mantinloc Shrine over El Nido's Bacuit Archipelago. 
<a id="more"></a>
<p>These links send you to the previous blogpost about the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/" title="Trip Information & Summary">Trip Information & Summary</a> and the next part of the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/" title="Travel Route for the Visayas and Manila">Travel Route for the Visayas and Manila</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Additional Information:</strong> Rating of the travel experiences in brackets from 1 (horrible) to 5 (awesome) with <font color="green">Highlights in green <font color="black">and  <font color="red">No-Go’s in red</font>.<br>
<font color="black"></font></font></font></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=zrYZfx3FSo48.k0hvSW6HcMlg"></iframe>
<h4>1. Parañaque, Manila, Luzon (4/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Megacity, Capital<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           16.12. - 17.12.14<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Manila does not have a good reputation, but more than any other metropolis in Southeast Asia it is an exciting melting pot of colonial heritage, business city, shopping malls, slum, Chinatown, American fast food restaurants, seafront, 24/7 nightlife and traffic jam.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> As most travelers will pass by Manila anyway it is worth staying here two to three days to explore the city. We decided to visit Manila at the end of our trip. To get around fast avoid the rush hour from 7 - 9 a.m. and 17 - 20 p.m.</p>
<p><strong>Accommodation:</strong>  <em><a href="http://www.domesticguesthouse.com" target="_blank" rel="external">DG Budget Hotel Naia</a></em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Hostel<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 25 € per night for AC room with double bed and shared bath<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> We chose this accomodation as it is very close to the Airport as we had another flight the next day;</p>
<p><strong>Shopping:</strong> <em><a href="http://www.dfp.com.ph/node/478" target="_blank" rel="external">Duty Free Philippines Fiestamall</a></em> (2/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Shopping Mall<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Next door is a Duty Free Mall, where you find literally all kind of western goods, but you will have to struggle your way out again. It might be a nice alternative to the small and pricy airport duty frees, but some articles like alcohol are definately way more expensive then in Europe or even local supermarkets. The only plus is the quite nice food court in there.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Unfortunately we couldn’t bring our guns…</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/firearms.jpg">
<h4>2. Manila, Luzon - Busuanga, Coron - Coron Town, Coron</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong> Transportation<br>
<strong>Date:</strong> 17.12.14<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 320 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 4 hours<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Off to Palawan!</p>
<blockquote>
<p><font color="red"><strong>1. Transportation:</strong>   Taxi to Manila Airport (1/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Taxi<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 5 km<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong>  5 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Before we could take off we got stuck in the worst traffic jam ever. We would have been faster by walking actually. There are crazy traffic conditions around the airport, especially to Terminal 3, where you can get only by taxi. Plan 1 - 2 hours additionally to get there in time!<br>
<font color="black"></font></font></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>2. Transportation:</strong>     17.12.14 / 12:15 - 13:20  Manila Ninoy Aquino - Busuanga<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> National flight (5J531)<br>
<strong>Airline:</strong> <em><a href="https://www.cebupacificair.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Cebu Pacific</a></em> (2/5)<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 300 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 1 hour<br>
<strong>Costs:</strong> 60 € + 4 € Terminal Fee<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Luckily the flight was also delayed… Cebu Pacific is a low cost airline, so no snacks or drinks are included, extra fee for overweight baggage, free WIFI at most airports<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Island life we are coming!</p>
</blockquote>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/island.jpg">
<blockquote>
<p><strong>3. Transportation:</strong> Van from Airport to Coron (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Van<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 25 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 30 min<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 3 €</p>
</blockquote>
<h4>3. Coron Town, Coron (4/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Town<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           17.12. - 18.12.14<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong>        Nice little town and starting point to surrounding islands; No beach nearby<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong>            Coron is a good place for wreck diving and island hopping trips. Better stay a few days if you are not in a hurry!</p>
<p><strong>Accomodation:</strong>   <em><a href="http://www.mttapyashotel.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Mount Tapyas Hotel</a></em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> B&amp;B<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 27 € per night for AC-room with double bed<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Nice view to the bay from the rooftop</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/coron.jpg">  
<p><strong>Food:</strong>       <em>Lolo Nonoy’s Food Station</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Cheap and authentic Filipino food. Unfortunately the beer boat for Coron sunk at the last taifun a few days ago, thats why they only served apple flavored beer, bah.</p>
<h4><font color="green"> 4. Coron Town, Coron - El Nido, Palawan (5/5)</font></h4>
<p><font color="green"><strong>Type:</strong>           Tour (<em>Sailing Paraw Expedition</em>)<br>
<strong>Tour Operator:</strong> <em><a href="http://www.taophilippines.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Tao Philippines</a></em> (5/5)<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           18.12. - 22.12.14<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong>       220 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong>       5 days<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Sailing boat from Coron to East Tangat Wreck (Snorkeling), Luson Wreck<br>
(Snorkeling), Patsy Island (1. Night), Evergreen (Snorkeling), Galoc Island (Kayaking), Buluang Village on Culion (2. Night), Buko Island (Beach), Sharon Island (Snorkeling), Ginto Island (3. Night), Kala Kala Island (Beach), Tao Farm in north Palawan (4. Night), Cadlao Island (Lagoon), Helicopter Island (Snorkeling), El Nido<br>
<strong>Number of Passengers:</strong>   26<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> The Balatik is really spacious and the largest traditional Paraw Sailboat in the Philippines.</font></p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/balatik.jpg">
<p><font color="green"><strong>Accommodation:</strong>  Single Beach huts or shared cottages on remote islands; The crew is setting up everything for the guests, including beddings, water and mosquito net<br>
<strong>Food:</strong>   Fresh fish on the way from fisherman villages, which will be cooked with vegetables and fruits coming from their own organic farms and on the boat. We had 4 days in a row of fresh seafood, which was very delicious, but we were really happy to enjoy an organic Lechon (roasted pork) at our last night at the Tao Farm.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Organic Lechon roasted for hours over open fire.</font></p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/pig.jpg">   
<p><font color="green"><strong>Entertainment:</strong>  You have to buy your drinks (beer and rum) in advance at the Tao<br>
office. There is ice on board, so your beer is always cold. At night you will get served a sundowner (rum with pineapple juice) and the rest is up to you. On one night we stayed in a fisherman village with karaoke bar, which was a lot o fun.<br>
<strong>Activities:</strong>     Snorkeling at reefs and wrecks, relaxing, swimming, get-together, kayaking to lonely islands, massage<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Lonely beaches at the Linapacan Group between Coron and Palawan with crystal clear water and wonderful nature over…</font></p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/beach.jpg">  
<font color="green">... and underwater:<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/snorkeling.jpg">  
<p><strong>Costs:</strong>          500 € including food, snorkel equipment &amp; accommodation<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> One of the best experiences we had in the Philippines. It is not cheap and not always comfortable, but it is totally worth it. You will visit empty islands, snorkel in untouched reefs and get in contact with local people. The paraw sailboat “Balatik” offers plenty of space and the crew is a cool bunch of locals. The founders of Tao have a really good concept to integrate local people in their business and operate an organic farm in one of their basecamps.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Even when your favorite trip dates are full, write them anyway, often there are still places available. Bring seasickness pills, wetbag, extra sunscreen and additional batteries, because there is mostly no electricity.<br>
</p></font><br>
<font color="black"><p></p>
<h4>5. El Nido, Palawan (4/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Town<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           22.12. - 28.12.14<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Backpackers hot-spot with laid-back atmosphere; The local beach itself is not very pleasant as it is completely filled with concrete buildings, but the surrounding limestone islands of the Bacuit Archipelago with wonderful beaches are breathtaking; Better book in advance during high season. There is also an airport in El Nido itself, heading from and to Manila. You can only book flights via emailing the airlines (<em>Island Transvoyager</em> and <em>SeAir</em> ) or the _<a href="http://www.elnidoboutiqueandartcafe.com/TravelCenter.html" target="_blank" rel="external">El Nido Boutique &amp; Art Cafe</a>_.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> There is no ATM in El Nido, so bring enough pesos with you. Alternatively you can get cash advance at the El Nido Boutique &amp; Artcafe or try to get cash at the local petrol station with your credit card.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> The nice town El Nido impresses more with its surrounding limestone cliffs then with its concrete beach.</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/el-nido.jpg">
<p><strong>Accommodation</strong>:  <em><a href="http://inngotouristinn.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Inngo Tourist Inn</a></em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> B&amp;B<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 33 € per night for AC-room with double bed and private bath<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Nice rooms with terrace and good breakfast; Free Wi-Fi, but connection is limited; Friendly staff &amp; owner</p>
<p><strong>Food:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Trattoria Atrove</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Great stone baked pizza for European prices; Often queue at the evening</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em><a href="http://www.lasalangane.com" target="_blank" rel="external">La Salangane</a></em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant<br>
Good Burgers (5€), fresh tuna sandwiches (5€) and French Menues (starting with 10€) served on a terrace above the sea come together with rum arrange (1€) and fast WIFI (free)<br>
**Tip:**La Salange is also a hotel with nice rooms.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Entertainment:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Pukka Bar</em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Restaurant, Bar &amp; Disco<br>
So called Reggae Bar, although the music is totally mixed. The best bar of El Nido is in the middle of the beach and packed at night</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>The Playground</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Bar<br>
Bar in the back of El Nido with fireplace, table tennis, dramatic view on one of the big limestones, unfortunately with many mosquitos and without toilets</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Activities:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Island Hopping Tour A</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Day tour<br>
<strong>Tour Operator:</strong> <em>Spider Booking</em><br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 24 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 6 hours<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Boat (Outtrigger boat to Miniloc Island with big and small lagoon, Shimizu Island and Seven Commandos Beach)<br>
<strong>Number of passengers:</strong> 15<br>
<strong>Food:</strong> Water, fresh grilled fish, chicken and pork rice, vegetable and fruits included<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 22€<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> The tour is nice, but not as good as Tour C i would say. The biggest disadvantage is that all boats go to the same places at the same time so the lagoons and beaches are very crowded.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Bring proper water shoes!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><font color="green"><em>Private Island Hopping Tour C</em> (5/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Tour<br>
<strong>Tour Operator:</strong> <em><a href="https://midnightsunelnido.wordpress.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Midnight Sun El Nido</a></em><br>
<strong>Distance:</strong>  44 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 6 hours<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Boat (Small outtrigger boat to Mantiloc Island with hidden beach &amp; secret beach, Tapiutan Island and Helicopter Island)<br>
<strong>Number of passengers:</strong> 4<br>
<strong>Food:</strong> Water, fresh grilled fish, chicken and pork, rice, vegetable and fruits included<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 24 € (95€ for 4 passengers)<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> We booked a private boat trip with Midnight Sun to choose the tour itinerary by our own. We had to walk 10 min to the Ca-alan Beach in the North of El Nido, where we started already at 8:00. This way we could enjoy the Hidden Beach all by our own and spend lunch at our private beach :)<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Bring proper water shoes and be aware that you can badly scratch yourself at Hidden and Secret Beach. We could recongize from peoples injuries, who did Tour C!<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Waiting for the lunch at our private beach, which we only had to share with our adopted dog Herbert.</font></p>
</li>
</ul>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/lunch.jpg">
<p><font color="black"></font></p>
<ul>
<li><em><a href="http://www.submariner-diving.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Submariner Diving Center</a></em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Dive<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Boat (Big outtrigger boat)<br>
<strong>Food:</strong> Curry, rice, water, tea and coffee included<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 64 € for 3 dives<br>
<strong>Dive sites:</strong> West Entulala (2/5) Paglugaban Island (3/5) South Miniloc (5/5)<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> West Entulala is just a wall dive, the rest reef dives. South Miniloc is full of fish schools and beautiful corals. Don’t expect sharks or anything bigger then turtles in El Nido.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sightseeing:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em>Las Cabanas</em> (3/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Beach<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Tricycle for 3 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Much nicer beach then in El Nido town. Unfortunately not much space and shadow.<br>
Tip: You can go via zip line to the offshore island nearby.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Nacpan Beach</em> (5/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> Beach<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Tricycle or rented motorbike.<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 10 € for a scooter rental<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> It takes 45 min - 1 hour to get there. Drive north and after around 30 min you should find a tree with sign to Nacpan beach pointing to the left. Follow the bumpy sandtrack until the end.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Rent a dirt motorbike, not a scooter as some parts are off-road and make sure the light is working and you have the number of the rental company in case of a flat tire, which happened to us.<br>
<strong>Picture:</strong> Nacpan Beach is a four km long stretch of white sand beach with a few food stall surrounded by palm trees.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/nacpan-beach.jpg">
<h4>6. El Nido, Palawan - Puerto Princessa, Palawan (2/5)</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           Transportation<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>           28.12.14<br>
<strong>Transportation:</strong> Van with AC<br>
<strong>Distance:</strong> 270 km<br>
<strong>Duration:</strong> 6 hours<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 9 €<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Drive during the day to see the landscape and passing by villages, otherwise the trip can become quite boring.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> Ask the driver if he can drop you somewhere in Puerto Princessa and take a tricycle from there, otherwise he will drive every passenger to their hotel, which took us another hour. Better take the Bus anyway, because the van will become very full. Make sure that you don’t have to sit on one of the small emergency seats.</p>
<h4>7. Puerto Princessa, Palawan</h4>
<p><strong>Type:</strong>           City<br>
<strong>Date:</strong>       28.12. - 29.12.14<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Not a very special city, but the only place to fly from Palawan directly to the Visayas (middle part of the Philippines).<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> You can make a guided firefly tour to the mangroves (1 hour, 20 €), a trip to the underground river (1 day, 30€) or a dive safari (7 days, 1500 €) to the Tubbataha Reef, one of the top dive spots in the <a href="http://world.sw" target="_blank" rel="external">world.sw</a></p>
<p><strong>Accommodation:</strong> <em><a href="http://www.puertopension.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Puerto Pension</a></em> (4/5)<br>
<strong>Type:</strong> B&amp;B<br>
<strong>Cost:</strong> 22€ per night AC-room with double bed and shared bath<br>
<strong>Comment:</strong> Nice wooden hotel with rooftop restaurant and courtyard with bar, who are dedicated to local nature conservation. Only the shared bathroom was a bit annoying, but they also offer rooms with private bath.<br>
<strong>Tip:</strong> You can book a tour to the Underground River.</p>
<p>Click here for the previous <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines/" title="Trip Information">Trip Information</a> or following part with the <a href="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Visayas-Manila/" title="Travel Route for the Visayas and Manila">Travel Route for the Visayas and Manila</a></p>
</font>]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<h2>II. Part: Trip Route (Palawan)</h2>
<p>Here you find the detailed description of the island hopping travel route through the Philippines, starting in Manila to Puerto Princessa. You can of course do the trip the other way around as well, TAO Philippines operates a few times per week in both directions.</p>
<img src="/2015/03/Travel-Route-Philippines-Palawan/view-from-matiloc-shrine.jpg">
View from the Mantinloc Shrine over El Nido's Bacuit Archipelago.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="El Ndio" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/El-Ndio/"/>
    
      <category term="Palawan" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Palawan/"/>
    
      <category term="Philippines" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Philippines/"/>
    
      <category term="Tao Philippines" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/Tao-Philippines/"/>
    
      <category term="island hopping" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/island-hopping/"/>
    
      <category term="travel guide" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/travel-guide/"/>
    
      <category term="trip inspiration" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/tags/trip-inspiration/"/>
    
      <category term="travel route" scheme="http://blog.trackfellas.com/categories/travel-route/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>